派拉蒙影业
维亚康姆公司
工厂[葡语]电影[西语]
通路实业电影
Access Industries FILM
译者注
1549年 天主教传教士圣·弗朗西斯·泽维尔(Saint Francis Xavier) 在日本鹿儿岛开始传教1613年 德川家康发布禁教令 幕府在全国禁止天主教 长崎云仙山区成为屠杀长崎地区天主教徒的场所 岛原天主教徒劫难始于此时
引自:http://blog.sina.com.cn/s/blog_3f8e0f520101iauv.html
译者注
1627年 松仓重政首创了"云仙地狱"的拷问方式将教徒倒悬温泉正上方 受高温硫磺毒气熏蒸在其气绝之前拖上缓和呼吸后 再吊回原位继续折磨
引自:http://www.sanada.net.cn/shiliao/shiliao_38.htm
译者注
1629年 水野守信首先于长崎实践以"踏绘"形式识别天主教徒的做法 所谓"踏绘"即把圣像置于受检人面前 强迫践踏
引自:http://www.sanada.net.cn/shiliao/shiliao_38.htm
译者注
"穴吊":将囚犯捆绑倒吊 头部插入大小如缸深坑耳后开口让血缓慢渗出 再用似枷木具从脖子两侧封住坑口埋住头部 持续多日致死
1634年 日本爆发反横征暴敛 反宗教迫害的农民大起义 即"岛原(天草)之乱"
引自:http://www.qulishi.com/huati/daoyuanzl/
沉默
我赞美你 主耶稣基督
Praise to you, Lord Jesus Christ.
开始
始め
1633年 愿主平安 赞美上帝
1633, pax Christi, praised be God.
尽管对我们而言 这片土地如今已无平静
Although for us, there is little peace in this land now.
在日本充满光明时 我从未了解过它
I never knew Japan when it was a country of light,
我也从未曾料到 它会变得如此黑暗
but I have never known it to be as dark as it is now.
我们的一切努力 都因一次次残害 压迫和折磨而付诸东流
All our progress has ended. A new persecution, new repression, new suffering.
他们在勺子底下钻了几个洞
They use ladles filled with holes, so the drops would come out slowly
让热水慢慢流下 带来更长久的痛苦
and the pain would be prolonged.
每一小注水 都像一块燃烧的煤炭
Each small splash of the water was like a burning coal.
奉行:官职 负责民政与司法 主持监察对外贸易等事务
长崎奉行 将四位修士和我们耶稣会的一位同伴 抓去了云仙
The Governor of Nagasaki took four friars and one of our own society to Unzen.
那里遍布温泉 日本人把它们称作地狱 一部分 我认为是为了嘲弄神父们
There are hot springs there. The Japanese call them "hells," partly, I think, in mockery
另一部分 我必须得说 是名副其实
and partly, I must tell you, in truth.
官差们让神父们背弃上帝 远离主爱的福音
The officials told our padres to abandon God and the gospel of His love.
但他们不仅拒绝弃教 还要求接受折磨
But they not only refused to apostatize, they asked to be tortured,
这样他们就能证明内心信仰的强大
so they could demonstrate the strength of their faith
证明上帝在自己心中
and the presence of God within them.
他们之中 有人在山上坚持了33天
Some remained on the mountain for 33 days.
他们的勇敢故事 为那些秘密坚守于此的神父带来了希望
The story of their courage gives hope to those of us priests who remain here in secret.
我们不会抛弃任何一位生活在恐惧中的基督徒
We will not abandon our hidden Christians -who live in fear. -"…who live in fear."
我们只会变得更加强大 在他的大爱之中
We only grow stronger in His love.
费雷拉从此音信全无
Ferreira is lost to us.
这是他最后一封信
This was his last letter.
为什么音信全无了?
Why lost?
这封信是在你们离开葡萄牙出去周游时送来的
This letter came to us when we were traveling from Portugal.
花费数年之久才抵达这里
It took years to reach us.
被藏匿过 偷渡过 赎回过
It was hidden, smuggled, ransomed.
最后由一位荷兰商人送到我手中
Finally, put into my hand by a Dutch trader,
他还带来了其它消息
who had other news as well.
是他还活着吗
He's alive?
是他已经弃教了
That he apostatized,
他公开谴责上帝 放弃信仰
that he denounced God in public and surrendered the faith,
现在作为一个日本人而生活着
and is now living as a Japanese.
这不可能
That's not possible.
费雷拉神父冒着生命危险 将我们的信仰传遍日本
Father Ferreira risked his life to spread our faith all over Japan.
没有他 就没有今天的我们
We're here today because of him.
他是我们当中最坚定的人
Yes. He was… He's the strongest of us.
他写下这些话时 正经历着最为残酷的迫害
He wrote those words during the most sweeping persecution of all.
现在情况变得更糟了
Now, things are even worse.
数以千计的人 死于我们所带去的信仰
Thousands are dead because of what we brought them.
更多的人选择了放弃它
Thousands more have given up the faith.
你说这个商人带来了消息 但这个消息未经证实 不是吗
You said this trader brought news, but it's not proven, is it?
这可能是谣言 用来进一步污蔑我们的信仰
It could be a slander created to further discredit our faith.
鉴于这个国家实施迫害的程度…
Given the extent of the persecution in that country…
是的 尊敬的神父 那里一定还有许多人需要我们
Yes. But, respectfully, there must be multitudes there
事实是 我们没有他的任何消息
-who need us, too. -And the fact, there has been no other word of him,
加上荷兰人带来的消息…
and the news brought by the Dutch…
那只是传言 神父…
Rumor, Father, only.
我确定这是真的
I must conclude it is true.
如果这是真的 神父
If it is true, Father,
对于耶稣会而言 这意味着什么?
what would it mean for the Jesuits?
对于整个欧洲天主教呢?
For the whole of Catholic Europe?
在我看来 我们的使命比以往更加紧急
It seems to me that our mission here is more urgent than ever.
我们必须出发 去寻找费雷拉神父
We must go find Father Ferreira.
我没有办法同意
I cannot allow that.
我们怎么能抛下自己的使命
How… How can we abandon our mission?
你的使命 葛尔贝神父 是找到费雷拉留下的消息
Your mission, Father Garupe, was to find word of Ferreira.
你已经找到了
You have found it.
恕我直言 神父 这封信里只说到那段黑暗的历史
Excuse me, Father, but this letter relates the most terrible history,
却未曾提及费雷拉本人的遭遇
but it says nothing of Ferreira himself.
他经历了什么 我们仍然不知道
Whatever happened to him is still unknown.
唯一知晓他命运的依据 不过是这一纸谣言
All that we know of his fate, is this one slander.
请允许我 范礼安神父
Permit me, Father Valignano, but…
我认为 我们的使命仍未结束
I… I believe our mission still stands.
你知道在岛原 有多少基督徒被统治者处决掉吗
Do you know how many Christians the authorities executed in Shimabara? most of them beheaded.
这对你们来说太危险了
No, it's far too dangerous for you.
但我们怎能对这位培植我们信仰的人置之不理?
Yes, but, Father, how do we neglect the man that nurtured us in the faith?
他为我们构建了整个世界
He shaped the world for us.
假若谣言是真的 那么费雷拉神父就是被诅咒了
And even if the slander should be true, then Father Ferreira is damned.
Yes.
我们别无选择 必须去拯救他的灵魂
We have no choice, but to save his soul.
这是你们发自内心的想法吗 你们两个?
This is in your hearts, then? Both of you?
是的  像我们的初心一般
-Yes. -It is. Like our first fervor.
那我只好相信 这是上帝的旨意
Then I must trust God has put it there.
他召唤你们去接受伟大的试炼
He calls you to a great trial.
从踏入那个国家的一刻起
The moment you set foot in that country,
你们就踏入了水深火热之中
you step into high danger.
你们将是最后两位被派遣过去的神父
You will be the last two priests to go.
两人之军
An army of two.
1640年 5月25日
May 25th, 1640.
愿主平安 赞美上帝
Pax Christi… God be praised.
范礼安神父 写下这段话时 我已经无法保证
Father Valignano, as I begin these lines, I cannot be sure that when they are done
这些信件最终能够送到你的手中
they will ever reach you.
但我希望你能保持对这次任务的信心
But I want to maintain your confidence in our mission
保持你对我们的信任
and vindicate your faith in us.
当心
Careful.
今天我们得到了好消息
Today, there was wonderful news.
你介绍的春先生 为我们找来一艘中国船
Your Mr. Chun has found us a Chinese boat.
它会将我们偷渡到日本
It will smuggle us into Japan.
他声称自己找到了澳门唯一的日本人
And he claims he's found the only Japanese in Macau,
来担任我们在日本最为重要的向导
to be our most valued guide in that country.
快来 这边走
Come on, this way.
终于 我们见到了第一个日本人
Finally, we meet our first Japanese.
他不太算是基督徒 你们见到便知
He's not much, you will see.
但不到两个月下来 他便是唯一一个了
But after almost two months, he's the only one.
嘿
Hey.
黑 起来
Hey, wake up.
快点 起来
Come on, get up.
他漂流在海上 葡萄牙人救了他
He was drifting on sea, Portuguese bring him.
他被困在这里 想要回到家乡
He's stuck here, wants to go home.
你真的是日本人吗
Is he… Are you really Japanese?
回答他们 你个傻子 他们是神父
Answer them, you fool. These are padres.
吉次郎 你个傻子 他们会带你回家
Kichijiro! You fool, they will take you home!
你家在哪里
Where is your home?
长崎
Nagasaki.
你做什么工作?
What's your work?
你们说什么他做什么
He will do what you say.
渔夫
Fisherman.
你会说我们的语言?
You know our language?
一点点
Little.
好的 一点点
Yes. Little.
你是从耶稣会神父那里学来的吗
You learned it from the Jesuit padres.
肯定是 所以 你是基督徒
You must have, so you're Christian?
不 不是基督徒
No! No Christian.
他会是个好向导 他也是基督徒
Good guide for you. He's Christian, too.
我不是基督徒
I'm not Christian!
基督徒都死了
Christian die!
他们
They…
他们都死在长崎了
They die in Nagasaki.
听我说 我们有钱
Listen to me. We have money.
如果你帮助我们 我们会带你回家
If you can help us, we can take you home.
我们可以带你回日本的家 你想回日本的家吗
We can take you home to Japan. Would you like to go home to Japan?
我想回家 不是为了钱
I want… I want to go home. Not for money.
日本 是我家人所在的国家
Japan is the country of my family!
我求你 别把我抛弃在这里 神父
I beg you. Don't abandon me here, Father.
求求你
Please!
带我回家
Take me home.
他会是一个好向导
He will be good guide.
-答应我 -我会把他洗干净 -带我回家 答应我
Promise me. -I'll clean him up. -They take me home! Promise me.
你做咩啊
我们的向导 他不可能是基督徒
Our guide… He can't be Christian.
他说他不是 但你能相信他说的任何话吗
He says he's not, but can you believe anything he says?
我甚至不愿相信他是日本人
I don't even want to believe he's Japanese.
他又对他们说
And He said to them, "Go ye into the whole world
马可福音16:15
你们往普天下去 传福音给万民听
"and preach the gospel to every living creature,
即使是对于这样的人
"even to one such as this."
我们的主如此命令道
So our Lord commanded,
当我准备遵从他的命令时 我眼前浮现出他的面容
and as I prepare to do His work, I see His face before me.
约翰福音21:15 耶稣三次命令彼得喂养照顾自己的小羊
他看上去 就像是他命令彼得时的样子
He looks as He must have when He commanded Peter,
喂养我的小羊
"Feed my lambs,
喂养我的小羊 喂养我的羊群
"feed my lambs, feed my sheep."
这让我着迷 我感受到如此强烈的大爱
It fascinates me. I feel such great love for it.
除了我们的心之外 我和葛尔贝没有要带到日本的行李
Garupe and I had absolutely no luggage to bring to Japan, except our own hearts.
在航行的波澜起伏中
And during the calm and storm of the voyage,
我回顾了迫害爆发以来的过去20年
I reflected upon the 20 years which has passed since the persecution has broken out.
日本的黑暗土壤已经掩埋了许多基督徒的哀嚎
The black soil of Japan is filled with the wailing of so many Christians.
基督徒的鲜血已经染遍大地
The red blood of priests has flowed profusely.
教堂的围墙已经分崩离析
The walls of the churches have fallen down.
日本
Shaba.
我们用了性命代价来信任这家伙
We've trusted that man with our lives.
耶稣信任过更糟糕的
Jesus trusted even worse.
快点
Hurry.
走
Come.
这里 这里 吉次郎 你要去哪里
Here, here! Kichijiro, where are you going?
吉次郎
Kichijiro!
他要去背叛我们了
He's going to betray us.
吉次郎
Kichijiro!
马太福音26:50
你要做什么 就快点做
Fact is fact. What you will do, do quickly.
神父
Padre?
快点 我们没时间了 快来 快来
Hurry. We have no time. No time! Come, come, come.
这是什么地方
What is this place?
友义村
Tomogi place.
日本?
-Japan? -Please be quick!
请快跟我来 不然会被疑教徒发现
So gentiles cannot see you. So, come.
疑教徒?
-Gentiles? -Yes.
过来 过来
Come, come. Quickly! Quick!
快点
Come!
抱歉 神父 太危险了 越来越多人被处决
I'm sorry, Padre. Too dangerous. There are more executions than ever.
如果他们知道我们是基督徒 我们就会被杀掉
If they know we're Christian, we will be killed.
主会听见你的
The Lord hears you.
是的 他把你们带来了
Yes. He sent you to us.
这边请
Please.
来 请进 请进
Please. Enter, enter.
谢谢你
Oh. Thank you.
我们准备了食物 希望你们能喜欢
We have little food, if you'd like.
明早之前 这里都很安全
You will be safe here until morning.
请坐下
Sit, sit! Please.
对不起 对不起
Oh. I'm sorry. I'm sorry.
你们是如何生存的?
How do you live like this?
我是说 这么危险的环境 你们如何过基督徒的生活?
I mean, how do you live as Christians when the danger is so great?
你们明白吗
You understand?
我们偷偷祈祷 我们还有爷爷大人
We pray in secret, but we have our Jiisama.
爷爷大人
-Jiisama? -Jiisama.
Jiisama.
谁是爷爷大人
Who is the Jiisama?
你带领他们吗 你带领这个村子吗
You lead them? You lead the village?
带领他们祈祷吗
-In prayer, in devotions? -Padre, too.
他唯一能实施的圣礼 就是洗礼
The only sacrament he can perform is baptism.
我们与爷爷大人一起做礼拜
We worship with the Jiisama.
我们把耶稣画像藏起来
We hide the Christian images.
但上帝仍旧能看见我们 是吗
Amen. But God still sees us. -Yes? -Yes.
即使我们没有神父? 但现在有了
Even though we do not have a priest until now.
请吃点东西
Ah! Please eat!
请吃吧
Please eat.
谢谢你
Thank you.
阿门
Amen.
这里的每个教徒 都属于我们的秘密教堂组织
Every Christian here is part of our secret church.
你们拥有的信仰如此强大
This… This faith… This faith you have is so strong.
你们如此勇敢
You have such courage.
只是这里才有这样的信仰 还是其他村子也有?
Is it only here that there is such faith or in other villages, too?
我们不了解其他村子 我们从来不出去
We do not know about other villages. We never go there.
你们不出去吗
Mmm, you don't go?
其他村子太危险了 你不知道该相信谁
Other villages are so dangerous. You do not know who to trust.
人人都害怕那个长崎奉行 井上大人
Everyone fears the Inquisitor Inoue-sama.
告发一个基督徒
Inform on Christian,
他们就会给你一百块银币
and they give you 100 pieces of silver.
告发一个修士 就是两百
200 for a Christian brother.
神父的话 三百
And for a priest, 300.
三百
Three hundred?
你一定要去其他村子
You must go to the other villages.
要让他们知道 神父又回来了
You must let them know that priests are here again.
我们又来到了日本 那样就太好了
That we are here in Japan, again, it will be good.
这里有一位神父
There was a, um, a padre,
叫费雷拉
who was here called Ferreira.
费雷拉神父
Father Ferreira.
你们听说过他吗
Have you heard of him?
和我们一样
Like us.
没有 没有?
-No. -No?
你不吃东西吗
You do not eat?
你才是喂养我们的人啊
It is you who feed us.
他们不敢带我们到大路附近的任何地方
They do not dare take us anywhere by the main road.
这样的躲藏 一定是个沉重无比的负担
To hide like this must be a terrible burden.
我自觉承受不起 从他们身上感受到的大爱
I was overwhelmed by the love I felt from these people,
即使他们无法在面容上表现出来
even though their faces couldn't show it.
长年的隐秘 已将他们的脸变为面具
Long years of secrecy have made their faces into masks.
为什么他们要遭受这么多苦难
Why do they have to suffer so much?
为什么上帝选择让他们来承受这份负担
Why did God make them to bear such a burden?
这里是最安全的
This is the safest here.
这个小屋是用来存放煤炭的
This hut for making charcoal.
当你听到这个声音
When you hear this sound…
就是我们来了
It will be us.
只要不是这个声音
If you hear anything else…
躲起来
Hide.
白天 我们紧紧关上小屋的门
During the day, we keep the door of our hut tightly closed
小心翼翼地不发出任何声响 以免被路过的人听见
and refrain from the slightest noise lest anyone passing outside may hear it.
直到黑暗降临 我们才能安全地回到村里
Only the dark makes it safe for us
去帮助村中的信徒
to go down into the village and minister to the faithful.
神父
Padre!
大人，拜托了
Please!
他们终于迎来了一位神父 可以宽恕他们的罪行
Finally, they had priests to forgive their sins.
大人?
大人
保佑我吧 神父 我犯下了罪
Bless me, Padre, for I have sinned.
忏悔吧
-Confession. -I have sinned.
再说一遍
什么 从头开始吗
我们整晚聆听他们的忏悔
We heard their confessions all night.
神父 但是之后
But then, Padre…
即使我们时常搞不清楚 他们在忏悔什么
Even though we could not always be sure what was being confessed.
现在 基督教带来了爱
And now, Christianity brought love.
带来了尊严 他们终于被当作上帝的子民 而非牲畜来对待
The dignity for the first time of being treated like God's creatures, not animals.
还带来了承诺 他们的一切艰苦努力都不会前功尽弃
And the promise that all their suffering would not end in nothingness,
而是换来救赎
but in salvation.
弥撒:基督教集体仪式 旨在纪念耶稣牺牲
那天深夜 我们主持了一次弥撒
We offer mass in the dead of night,
就像他们在地洞里做过的一样 静悄悄地
just as they did in the Catacombs. Quietly.
以圣父 圣子 圣灵之名 阿门
In nomine Patris, et Filii, et Spiritus Sancti. Amen.
…圣灵之名 我为你洗礼 阿门
-Amen. -Amen.
我们现在 都和上帝一起 在天锅了吗
We now always God in paraíso?
天锅?
Paraíso?
对 天国?
-Yes. -Paradise?
对 天国
Yes, paradise.
现在? 对
-Now? -Yes.
不 不是现在
No. No.
但上帝现在就在那里 永远都在
But God is there now. And forever.
他为我们所有人都准备了一个地方 即使是现在
He prepares a place for us all, even now.
万分感谢
ありがとうございました
对不起 塞巴斯蒂安 我太没耐心了
I'm sorry, Sebastian, for my impatience.
我为我的垂头丧气感到羞耻
I'm ashamed of my frustration.
那个孩子正被上帝的恩慈所保护着
The child is safe in the grace of God now
这才是最重要的
and that is what is important.
而你这个耶稣会士 当得的确糟糕
And you're a bad Jesuit.
真是受够了天天被困在这里
Sick of being trapped in here all day.
吃吧
Eat.
我们连费雷拉神父是生是死都不知道
We don't even know if Father Ferreira is alive or dead.
村民们连他的名字都没听说过
The villagers never even heard of him.
这些人整天都这么害怕
These people are so frightened.
他们是不是只剩恐惧了
There's fear over their head,
还有虱子
and lice.
他们还有我俩 我们去安抚他们
They have us, we comfort them.
我们还能安抚他们多久?
How much longer can we do that?
是我们自己要求这次任务的 弗朗西斯科
We asked for this mission, Francisco.
我们在祷告时祈求了上帝的祝福
We prayed for this in the exercises.
他已经听见我们了 他现在也能听见我们
God heard us then, and He hears us now.
但愿他能带我们找到费雷拉 然后就能知道真相了
Well, then, may He guide us to Ferreira so we can know the truth.
你觉得费雷拉真的有可能无力抵抗
You think it's possible that his strength gave out
然后趴在井上奉行的面前俯首称臣
and he groveled to this Inquisitor Inoue,
像条狗一样跪着吗
went on his knees like a dog?
那依旧只是个传言
That's still just a rumor.
就算井上是人尽皆知的恶魔
Even if this Inoue is the devil everyone claims,
费雷拉也会毫不犹豫地反抗他
Ferreira would stand up to him.
我们俩必须有一个人去长崎找他
One of us must go to Nagasaki and find him.
太危险了
It's too dangerous.
对我们来说 对那些保护我们的人来说
For us, for the people who shelter us.
我们让吉次郎去打探消息 然后我们再行动
We send Kichijiro, he brings back word we can act on.
你疯了吗
Are you mad?
他在哪里?
Where is he?
他从没来过这里
He's never here.
他总是烂醉如泥 你知道他不值得信任
He's always drunk, you know he can't be trusted.
你想怎么办 我们必须去寻找费雷拉神父
What do we do? We must do something to find Father Ferreira.
我们出去吧
Let's go out.
冒一次险吧 就出去一会儿
Let's risk it. Just for a moment.
看
Look.
这是上帝的暗示啊
That's God's sign.
别动
Don't move.
那边有人在看我们
Someone's here watching us.
跑
神父
Padre?
别去 这信号不对
No, no, no. That's not the signal.
神父 请不要害怕 没关系的
Padre. Do not be afraid. It's all right.
我们不会伤害你们
We won't hurt you.
我们是基督徒 神父 基督徒
We Christian, Padre. Christian!
基督徒
Christian.
我们需要你们
We need you.
别去 塞巴斯蒂安 别 别
No, no! Sebastian, hey! No! Sebastian!
噢 神父
Padre.
我们吓到了你们 真是对不起
We have frightened you. We are sorry.
我们想邀请你们去我们的村子 去五岛
We want to ask you to come to our village. To Gotō.
村里的人们怀念我们的信仰
People miss our faith there.
我们的孩子需要你们
Our children need you.
我们没有弥撒 没有忏悔
We have no mass, no confession.
唯一能做的只有祈祷
All we can do is pray.
你们怎么知道我们在这里
How did you know we were here?
谁告诉你们的 是我们的信徒吗
Who told you? Was it one of the faithful?
是我们村子里的一个基督徒 吉次郎
It was a Christian of our village. Kichijiro.
吉次郎?
Kichijiro?
我们的吉次郎?
Our… Our Kichijiro?
他说 他和你们一起来到这里的
He said he came here. With you.
但他不是基督徒
Yes, but he's not a Christian.
他是的
Yes, he is.
这是真的 他当着长崎奉行井上大人的面 谴责上帝
It's true. He spoke against God to the Inquisitor, Inoue-sama.
但那是八年前了
But that was eight years ago.
他全家人都被下令处死
His whole family was put to death.
他嘴上声称弃教
He spoke against God.
但心里还是个教徒
But he still believes.
不行
No. No.
他们需要神父到五岛去
They need priests on Gotō.
不行 神父
-No, Padre.
不行 不行 神父
-No, no, Padre.
我们会回来的
-We will return here.
我们不了解五岛的人
I do not know the people of Gotō.
所以我不知道他们能否信任
So I do not know they can be trusted.
他们是基督徒 和我们一样
These are Christians. Like us.
吉次郎让他们过来的
Kichijiro told them to come here.
我不知道为什么
I'm not sure why.
他为什么总是没事找事?
Why does he do anything?
把我们带来友义村的 也是吉次郎
Kichijiro brought us here to Tomogi.
我们只去几天而已
It'll only be for a few days.
请留下一个吧 留在这里 拜托了
But one will stay here? Please.
-嗯 -好
-Huh. -Yes.
我们快跟不上他们了
We're losing them.
这就对了
That's right.
旅途中所积攒的恐惧 逐渐地消失了
The fear I'd felt on the journey faded away.
因为前来迎接的他们 几乎就像安全着陆时的我一样欣喜
Because the joy which greeted me was almost as great as my own.
甚至吉次郎的样子都变得令人愉悦了起来
Even the sight of Kichijiro was somehow welcome.
来
Come.
感谢上帝将我带到这里
I thanked God for bringing me here.
那一天 信徒们迎来了新的希望
On that day, the faithful received fresh hope.
我也焕然一新了
And I was renewed.
（葡萄牙语）
他们来到我的身边
And they came to me.
不仅是五岛
Not only from Gotō, for the Christians made their way
其他村子的基督徒 也穿山越岭来到这里
through the mountains from other villages.
我感到上帝离我如此之近
I felt God Himself was so near.
生命在这里是如此艰难
Their lives here are so hard.
他们像牛马一样劳作 像牛马一样无声地死去
They live like beasts and die like beasts.
但耶稣不是为至善至美的事物而献身的
But Christ did not die for the good and beautiful.
那太过容易了
That is easy enough.
真正困难的 是为那些悲惨而堕落的灵魂献身
The hard thing is to die for the miserable and corrupt.
而在这里 我知道自己是他们中的一员
But here, I knew I was one of them
我分享着他们灵魂中的欲望
and I shared the hunger of their spirit.
我的祷告在五岛得到了回应
Another prayer was answered on Gotō.
我在那里 第一次打听到费雷拉神父的消息
It was there I learned the first real news of someone who might know of Father Ferreira.
神父 费雷拉
Padre Ferreira.
神父 费雷拉 对
对 你听说过他吗 听过
-Yes, do you know him? -Yes.
你认识他吗
-You know him? -Yes.
你见过他吗 见过
-You've seen him? -Yes.
什么时候
When?
费雷拉神父曾在长崎新町 为被弃路旁的婴孩和病人搭建居所
他搭了屋子 为那些婴海和…
He made a pray for infant and the…
婴海?
-Infant. -Eu-fot? Infant.
宝宝
-Baby! Baby! -Infant.
婴孩 抱歉 婴孩
-Yeah! -Sorry, infant.
还有病人
And, uh, sick, sick.
在新町
At, uh, Shimachi.
新町
-Shimachi. Shimachi. -Shimachi.
那还是在禁教令颁布之前
But, uh, that was before the trouble.
新町在哪里
Oh, where is this?
长崎附近
-Near Nagasaki. Nagasaki. -Nagasaki.
但那里很危险的
But so dangerous. Dangerous to go.
不说了吗 我不知道 我不知道
No? I don't know. I don't know.
他们极度渴望带有信仰符号的实物
They are desperate for tangible signs of faith.
所以我尽可能满足了他们
So I provided what I could.
我担心他们将这些信仰符号 看得信仰本身更加重要
I worry they value these poor signs of faith more than faith itself.
但我又怎么能拒绝他们呢
But how could we deny them?
最后 我不得不把自己的念珠拆开
And finally, I had to part with my rosary.
吉次郎 吉次郎
Kichijiro! Kichijiro!
在五岛 我完全忙不过来
In Gotō, I was completely overwhelmed.
我施洗了一百多个成人和孩子 倾听了无数次忏悔
I baptized over 100 adults and children, heard confessions without number.
但我感觉最需要我的 其实是吉次郎
But it was from Kichijiro that I felt the greatest need.
你没有拿我的念珠
You did not take the rosary.
我不配拿
I did not deserve it.
为什么
Why?
因为你否认了上帝的存在吗
'Cause you denied God?
是的
Yes.
但只是为了生存
But only to live!
我的所有家人
My whole family…
那个井上奉行 企图让我们放弃信仰
The Inquisitor, Inoue, wanted us to give up our faith.
让我们用脚去践踏基督圣像
Stamp on Jesus with our foot.
就踩一脚 轻踩一下
Just once, just pressed.
可他们不愿意
But they would not.
但我踩了
But I did.
可我不能抛弃他们 就算我抛弃了上帝
But I could not abandon them, even if I had abandoned God.
于是我看着他们死去
So I watched them die.
不管我往哪里走
Wherever I go,
我都能看到熊熊的火焰 闻到肉体的焦味
I see the fire and smell the flesh.
当我第一次遇到 您和葛尔贝神父时
When I saw you and Padre Garupe, for the first time,
我开始相信
I started to believe
上帝会带我回来
that God might take me back!
因为在我的梦里
Because in my dreams
火焰已经不再那么灼目了
the fire was no longer so bright!
你想让我现在听你忏悔吗
You want me to hear your confession now?
保佑我吧 神父
Bless me, Padre,
我犯下了罪
for I have sinned.
在五岛的那六天 以及吉次郎重新拾起的信仰
Those six days at Gotō and Kichijiro's renewal of faith
让我感受到 我的生命充满了价值
made me feel that my life was of value
我能够实实在在地 帮助这个国家的人民
and that I could really be of use to people in this country
这个处在世界尽头的国家
at the ends of the Earth.
官差 奉行大人派来的 他们就在村子里
Men from the Inquisitor, they are in the village.
他们抓了一藏
They took Ichizo.
我们听说
你们之中有些人
和这个可怜的家伙一样
是基督徒
但我们每年都有缴税
也为国家尽了义务
我们信奉寺庙里的佛祖
我很清楚
你们都是善良的子民
我们只是想找出
那些信奉
非法信仰的人
还有那些
包庇他们的人
迟早 我们会找出这些人的
想想举报的酬劳吧
这么多的银币
别一副担惊受怕的样子
给他们三天时间吧
给他松绑
你们有三天时间
我们先放此人一马
但如果三天后 我们还一无所获
除了他
我还会再带走三个人质
这四个人质会被押送到长崎
另外
这三个人中
必须要有你
我们不怕死 神父
No, we are not afraid to die, Padres,
我们绝对不会供出你们的
and we will never surrender you.
没有人应该送死
No one should die.
对 但是不管你们走还是留 我们都有危险
No. But we will be in danger whether you go or stay.
所以留下来吧 留下来
So stay. Stay.
我们永远不会供出你们的
We will never surrender you.
我们留在这里的话 他们还会再回来的
They'll keep coming back if we stay.
他们会毁掉整个村子 杀光你们所有人
They could destroy the entire village and kill you all, while we hide.
不会的
No.
我们别无选择了 茂吉 这是唯一能做的事
Yes, we have no choice, Mokichi. It is the only thing to do.
我们能替你们把危险引开
This will draw the danger away from you.
我们可以躲去吉次郎的岛上
We can hide on Kichijiro's island.
我的岛上?
My island?
不 躲在那里和躲在这里 没有任何区别
No. There is no difference between there and here.
他们会登上五岛 挨家挨户搜查
They will come to Gotō. They will search.
结果都是一样的
Same thing will happen.
不行
他们应该离开
两位神父应该离开
这样 我们就能活下来
你不能这样说
他们是来传播耶稣教义的
我们不能把他们供出去
他们为我们做了这么多 不能让他们受井上大人的折磨
他们给我们带来了危险
要不是神父来了 我们也不会有这么多麻烦
安静 安静
我们要保护
神父们
你们留下来
You will stay.
现在必须再选出两人来加入我们
我 茂吉 再找两个人质
Me, Mokichi, and two more hostages.
谁愿意同我和茂吉一起
作为人质 去荣耀主的圣名?
吉次郎不是我们村的
为什么不让他去
对啊
为了我们所有人 你会去吗
那些官差不会太为难你的
他们只想要友义村的人
他不是村里的人
可能就是他告密的
我没有告密
神父 告诉他们
I'm not an informer!
我忏悔了所有的罪孽
I confessed all my sins.
如果你已经得到了主的庇佑
就要像他一样
用你的生命去荣耀他
没错
荣耀? 我听不懂你在说什么
真正的基督徒肯定听得懂
我要打爆你的脑袋
拜托你了
跟他们走吧
求求你
神父
Padre?
神父 如果我们被逼迫着
Pa… Padre. If we are forced to trample
去践踏圣像 在踏绘仪式上
on the Lord, on the fumie…
踏绘:践踏圣像以示背弃基督教的仪式
你要向上帝祈求勇气 茂吉
You must pray for courage, Mokichi.
但如果我们没有如他们所愿
But if we do not do what they want,
村子里的每个人都会有危险
then it can be danger for everyone in the village.
他们会被关到牢里
They can be put in prison!
永远不能回来
Taken away forever.
我们应该怎么做
What should we do?
踏吧 踏吧 踏下去没关系的
Trample. Trample. It's all right to trample.
你在说什么
What are you saying?
不可以
You can't!
茂吉 你不可以踏
Mokichi, you can't.
这是我做给爷爷大人的 我们只有这个
I make this for the Jiisama. It was all we had.
在你们到来之前
Until you came.
拿着吧 拜托了
Take this. Please.
以耶稣的圣名
In Jesus' name.
你的信仰给予我勇气 茂吉
Your faith gives me strength, Mokichi.
我希望我能给予你同样多的勇气
I wish I could give as much to you.
我强烈地爱着上帝
My love for God is strong.
这和信仰是一回事吗
Could that be the same as faith?
是的 是的 一定是的
Yes. Yes. I think it must be.
这些人 是世界上最忠诚于上帝的臣民
These people are the most devoted of God's creatures on Earth.
范礼安神父 我在此忏悔 我陷入了疑惑
Father Valignano, I confess, I began to wonder.
上帝让我们接受考验 来测试我们 他所做的一切 自然都是好的
God sends us trials to test us and everything He does is good.
耶稣是上帝之子
我也祈祷自己能够接受考验 像他的儿子一样
And I prayed to undergo trials like his son.
可是为什么 这些村民的考验要如此可怕?
But why must their trial be so terrible?
为什么 当我正视自己的内心时
And why, when I look in my own heart,
我给予他们的回答 听起来是如此无力?
do the answers I give them seem so weak?
踩
他们全部按照要求做了
All of them did as they were commanded.
但这并不够
But it was not enough.
你们觉得我们是这么好骗的吗
我们注意到了
你们的呼吸
刚刚突然急促起来
不可能
我们是佛教徒
行
那我们换个方式
朝它吐唾沫
然后说 你们所谓的圣母玛利亚
是个婊子
你也是个基督徒
一藏不愿意那样做
Old Ichizo would not do it.
茂吉也不愿意
Mokichi could not.
但吉次郎做到了其他人没做到的
But Kichijiro succeeded where the rest failed.
我必须相信 他和其他人一样 也经受着磨难
I must believe he suffered along with the others.
你也是个基督徒
他们全部都是
基督徒
抓住他们
他们被喂了米酒
They were given sake,
就像罗马士兵给临死的耶稣喂了醋一样
as the Roman soldier offered vinegar to the dying Christ.
我祈祷他们能够记得 主所经受的磨难
I prayed they remembered our Lord's suffering
并从中获得力量和慰藉
and took courage and comfort from it.
上帝
天国
神圣的上帝
请接纳爷爷大人的灵魂吧
爷爷大人的苦难结束了
接纳他吧 主啊
主啊
在您的荣耀下
求您了
耶稣啊
整整四天之后 茂吉才死去
It took Mokichi four days to die.
他在死前唱了一首圣歌
At the end, he sang a hymn.
那一刻他是世上唯一的声音
His voice was the only sound.
聚集在海滩上的村民们 始终保持着沉默
The people of the village who were gathered on the beach were always silent.
村民们被密切监视着
The people were watched closely
不让他们将三人的遗体 以基督教的方式埋葬
so the bodies could not be given a Christian burial.
茂吉的遗体吸满了水 冒了很久的烟才燃烧起来
Mokichi's body was so heavy with water, it turned the flames to smoke before it finally caught fire.
所有残留的骨头都被冲进海里 不让后人瞻仰崇敬
Any bones that remained were scattered in the ocean so they could not be venerated.
范礼安神父 他们的死不是毫无意义的
Father Valignano, you will say that their death is not meaningless.
上帝一定听到了他们死前的祷告
Surely God heard their prayers as they died.
但他听到他们的哀嚎了吗
But did He hear their screams?
这些村民承受了如此之多 我要如何向他们解释上帝的沉默?
How can I explain His silence to these people who have endured so much?
我需要竭尽全力 来想通这个问题
I need all my strength to understand it myself.
这可能是我的最后一封报告信了 神父
This may be my last report to you, Father.
今天我们听说官差在山中搜寻我们
Today we hear the guards are in the mountains looking for us.
出于安全考虑 我们决定分头撤离
So we have decided it will be safer to separate.
你说得对 我们离开的话 他们还有机会活下来
They were right. If we left, they might still be alive.
别这么说 那不是事实
Don't say that. That's not true.
我们也无法否认 留下就是死路一条
And we cannot doubt, that will be our death.
我们是放弃了吗 这就是我们的选择吗 我们是在逃跑吗
Are we giving up? Is that what we are doing? -Are we running away? -No.
哪怕有人已经为我们而死
After people have died for us.
他们不是为我们而死的
They did not die for us.
葛尔贝 他们不是为我们而死的
Garupe, they did not die for us.
我觉得自己像个懦夫
I feel like a coward.
我的爱与你同在
My love goes with you.
我祈求自己能像你一样坚强
I pray to be as strong as you.
平户:位于长崎县西北部
葛尔贝神父会前往平户 去继续执行任务
Father Garupe will make for Hirado to continue the mission.
我则返回五岛
And I will return to Gotō.
弗朗西斯科 活下去 活下去
Francisco, stay alive. Stay alive.
神父 我祈求您的宽恕 原谅我的懦弱与疑惑
Father, I ask forgiveness for my weakness and my doubt.
我祈求您为我和葛尔贝神父仁慈祷告
And I ask you to remember Father Garupe and me in your masses and in your prayers.
您顺从的孩子
Your obedient son.
我想象着您的儿子
I imagine your Son
被钉在十字架上
nailed to the cross.
我的嘴唇似乎尝到了醋的味道
My mouth tastes like vinegar.
那是五岛吗
Is that Gotō?
天国的圣父 我赞美您的名
Father in heaven, praised be thy name.
我只不过是个带来灾祸的外国人
I'm just a foreigner who brought disaster.
这就是现在他们眼中的我
And that's what they think of me now.
圣方济各:天主教方济各会创始人 将天主教传播到日本的第一人
我梦见了圣方济各
I dream of our St. Francis.
他在这里所建立的所有荣光 都遭遇了怎样的变故?
What happened to all the glorious possibility he found here?
我为主做过什么
What have I done for Christ?
我在为主做什么
What am I doing for Christ?
我要为主做什么
What will I do for Christ?
我感觉自己是那么动摇
I feel so tempted.
动摇到近乎绝望
I feel so tempted to despair.
我很害怕
I'm afraid.
您的沉默是那么沉重
The weight of your silence is terrible.
我祈祷着 却迷失了
I pray, but I'm lost.
还是说 没有人在倾听我的祈祷?
Or am I just praying to nothing?
没有人
Nothing.
因为您并不在那里
Because you are not there.
我祈求你的宽恕
I pray for your forgiveness.
今后如果我的报告中断了
If my report now comes to an abrupt end,
不要以为我们已死
do not think that we are dead.
如果葛尔贝和我死了
Forif Garupe and I die,
日本的教会将与我们一同消亡
the Japanese church dies with us.
我以为我被人跟踪了
I thought I was being followed.
你还好吗 神父
Are you all right, Padre?
抱歉
Sorry.
神父
Padre?
你为什么回来这里 神父
Why did you come back here, Padre?
这地方很危险
This place is dangerous.
我们必须小心谨慎
We must be careful.
他们用三百块银币悬赏你
There is a price of 300 pieces of silver for you.
犹大:耶稣门徒 因三十块银币出卖耶稣
三百 犹大也才拿了三十
Three hundred. Judas got only 30.
在不远的村子里 还有一些基督徒
There are Christians near the villages. Not far.
我们可以躲去那里 我来照顾你
We can hide there. I will take care of you.
吃吧 请吃
Take it. Please.
您一定很饿了
You must be so hungry.
茂吉和我的家人 一直都那么坚强
Mokichi and my family stayed strong.
我太懦弱了
I am so weak.
是吗 瞧你把自己照顾多好
Are you? You can certainly look after yourself.
我不是只为了自己
Not to be selfish.
我和你一样
I am like you.
我哪里也去不成
I have nowhere else to go.
在这样的一个世界中
Where is the place for a weak man
弱小的我还能去哪里?
in a world like this?
你想向茂吉和一藏忏悔吗
You want to confess for Mokichi and Ichizo?
以圣父 圣子 圣灵之名
In nomine Patris, et Filii, et Spiritus Sancti.
马太福音26:50
你要来做的事 快做吧
"What you will do, do quickly."
这是您的儿子在最后的晚餐上对犹大所说的话
Your Son's words to Judas at the Last Supper.
当时他是否感到愤怒?
Was he angry when he said them?
还是说 这些话源自他的爱?
Or did they come from love?
您没事吧 神父?
Are you all right, Padre?
您看上去很疲惫 我没事
-You seem so tired. -I'm all right.
那条鱼好咸
The fish you gave me was so salty.
我渴了
I thirst.
什么 我渴了
-What? -I thirst.
约翰福音19:28
主也这么说过
-Our Lord said that. -Yes.
我去取些水来
-I get some water. -Ah.
吉次郎
Kichi…
我去取水 吉次郎
-I get water. -Kichijiro!
吉次郎
Kichijiro.
抱歉 我把水洒了 神父
Oh. Sorry, I dropped the water, Padre.
我以为您出事了
I thought something was wrong.
但是别担心
But, never mind.
有条小溪就在附近
There is a stream just nearby.
您想喝多少都可以
You can drink as much as you like.
这边
Here.
神父 原谅我
Padre, forgive me.
神父
Padre?
我祈求上帝的宽恕
I pray for God's forgiveness.
他会宽恕吗 哪怕是我?
Will he forgive? Even me?
上帝保佑
Blessed be God.
你叫什么名字
What is… What is your name?
莫妮卡
-Monica. -Ah.
奥古斯丁:天主教四大圣师之一 天主教奥斯定会创始人
和奥古斯丁的母亲同名
Like the mother of Augustine.
受洗名:基督徒在洗礼时所取的圣名
这是我受洗的名字 这位是胡安
My baptismal name. This man is Juan.
他希望他的受洗名 和我们的神父一样
He wanted his name to be like our priest Juan,
在云仙去世的胡安神父
who died at Unzen.
会有越来越多人像他一样死掉的
There will be many more joining him.
你懂吗
You understand.
为什么 为什么你要这样看着我?
Why are you… Why are you looking at me like that?
你们为什么如此平静?
Why are you so calm?
我们全都要死了 就像他那样
We are all about to die! Like that!
抱歉 我很抱歉
I'm sorry.
谢谢 谢谢你的食物
I'm sorry. Thank you. Thank you for the food.
但是 神父
Padre…
我们的神父
Our father,
胡安神父 他说我们死后会升上天锅
Padre Juan said if we die, we will go to paraíso.
天国 是的没有错
Paradise. Yes, that's right.
难道死亡不是件好事吗
Isn't it good to die?
天国比这里好多了
Paraíso is so much better than here.
没有饥饿 没有病痛 没有赋税 没有辛苦劳作
No one hungry. Never sick. No taxes. No hard work.
是的 当然了
Yes. Of course.
胡安神父是对的
Padre Juan was right.
在天锅不用辛苦劳作
There is no hard work in paraíso.
连劳作都没有
There is no work at all.
也没有赋税
There is no taxes.
没有苦难
There is no suffering.
我们会与上帝同在
We all will be united with God.
痛苦也没有了
There will be no pain.
希望你们能别再给我 制造那么多麻烦了
拜托
在我们这个年纪
不应该在这种大热天 长途跋涉这么远
还有这些灰尘
今年尤其严重
这些都是非常没有必要的
拜托你们稍微花点功夫
站在我们的角度理解一下
我们并非仇恨你们
这都是你们自作自受
你们也完全可以
自己拯救自己的
没必要茫然若失
我会给你们时间好好想想
然后请给我一个合理的答复
走吧
不 不算你
No, not you.
你留下
You stay.
我跟他们说的 你听得懂吗
You understood what I was saying to them?
你的日语够好吗
Your Japanese is good enough?
我注视过你的双眼
-I saw your eyes. -Oh.
你觉得你都看见了什么
And what did you think you saw there?
他们都是蠢货 那些农民
They're fools. Those peasants.
主啊 请保佑他们远离苦难 一路平安
Lord, spare them suffering and keep them safe in Your hand.
他们可以无休止地讨论一整天 最后都统一不了意见
They can talk among themselves without end. And decide nothing.
但你是明白人 不是吗
But you understand, don't you?
想说什么就直说吧
Just say what you mean.
他们能否被释放 全都取决于你
That it all depends on you whether they are set free,
只需要你说一个字
if you say just one single word.
在他们面前 否认你的信仰
Show them. Deny your faith.
要是我拒绝 你就杀了我吗
So what if I refuse? You kill me?
基督教神学家德尔图良的名言
殉道者的鲜血就是教会的种子
The blood of martyrs is the seed of the church.
就像你在大村和长崎所屠杀的神父那样
Just like the priests you slaughtered in Omura and Nagasaki.
处决神父给我们带来了教训
We learned from our mistake.
而处决掉农民 只会让他们更加冥顽不灵
Killing the priests and killing the peasants makes it worse.
如果他们能够为上帝而死 他们会觉得 这会让他们变得更加强大
If they can die for their God, they think it only makes them stronger.
如果你觉得必须处罚谁的话 处罚我一个人吧
If you feel you must punish someone, punish me alone.
你根本就不是一个好神父
You do not speak like a good priest!
如果你是个真男人 真正的好神父
If you were a real man, a truly good priest,
你应该对那些基督徒心生慈悲 为他们着想
you should feel pity for the Christian.
不是吗 神父? 不是吗
Isn't that so, Padre, isn't that so?
你一人荣耀的代价 是他们的苦难折磨
The price for your glory is their suffering.
神父?
Padre,
赞美主 我们的天父
praise be to God, our Father.
赞美主
Praise be to Him.
我的葡萄牙语 是从你们的卡布拉尔神父那里学来的
The Portuguese language was a gift of your Father Cabral.
我受命来为你做翻译
I have been asked to interpret on your behalf.
我们担心 你的证词会漏掉某些细节
There was concern that we might miss certain subtleties in your testimony
如果他们只让你说日语
if you were told to speak only in Japanese.
证词? 我…
Testimony? Uh…
我们希望尽可能公平
We want it to be fair.
而且我们对英语的掌握
And we do have a better grasp of your language
比你们的日语要好
than you do of ours.
卡布拉尔神父就从来只会说 "谢谢你"
Father Cabral never managed much more than arigataya.
他一直在这里教书 却始终不愿学习
All the time he lived here, he taught, but would not learn.
他瞧不起我们的语言 食物 和我们的习俗
He despised our language, our food, our customs.
我不像他 我和卡布拉尔不一样
I'm not like him. I'm not like Cabral.
真的? 真的
-Really? -Yes.
我们有自己的信仰 神父
We have our own religion, Padre.
不 不 可惜你没有注意到
Pity you did not know this yet.
只是不同角度的思考方式罢了
No. No, no. We just think a different way.
是啊
True.
你认为我们的佛只是凡人
You believe our Buddhists are only men.
只是人类而已
Just human beings.
佛也是会死的
Even a Buddha dies.
和所有人一样
Like all men.
他不是造物主 你太无知了
-He is not the Creator. -You are ignorant.
神父 只有基督徒才会视佛为凡人
Padre, only a Christian would see Buddhists simply as men.
我们的佛是凡人可以达到的
Our Buddha is a being which men can become.
一种超脱自我的存在 只要他能战胜自己的幻象
Something greater than himself if he can overcome all his illusions.
而你 却对你的幻象执迷不悟 还称之为"信仰"
But you cling to your illusions and call them faith.
不 你不明白
No, you don't understand.
任何人 只要遵循上帝的诫条 他就能…
If any man follows God's commandments,
过着平和喜乐的生活
then he can live a peaceful and joyous life.
不 不 我明白
I do. I do understand.
神父 这非常简单
Padre, it is perfectly simple.
你听说过这个词吗
Have you heard that word?
意思是 "跌倒" "投降"
It means fall down, surrender,
"放弃信仰"
give up the faith.
也就是你们口中的 "弃教"
Apostatize, as you say.
放弃吧
Do it.
如果你不弃教 百姓们就会被吊在洞里
If you don't apostatize, the prisoners will be hung over the pit.
在你弃教之前 他们会一直吊在那里 直到鲜血滴尽
Until you do, their lives bleeding away drop by drop.
有的人能撑好几天
Some last for days, some do not.
有的人很快就死了
They die.
他们就是这样对待波洛神父和卡索拉神父的 你听说过他们吗
They tortured Fathers Porro and Cassola over the pit. Have you heard of them?
还有个叫佩德罗的 当然还有费雷拉
There was one called Pedro, too. And Ferreira of course.
费雷拉?
Ferreira?
你认识他吗
Did you know him?
我听说过他
I have… I have heard of him.
这不奇怪 现在全日本都知道他
No doubt. He's well-known all over Japan now.
一个神父 有着日本名字 有着日本老婆
The priest with the Japanese name and the Japanese wife.
我不相信 你可以问任何人
-I don't believe you. -You can ask anyone.
长崎的人们都认识他 景仰他
People in Nagasaki point him out and marvel.
他现在相当受人尊敬
He's held in great esteem now,
我相信 这就是他来这里的初衷
which, I believe, is why he came here in the first place.
自以为是的家伙 和别的神父一个样
也就是说 他最终也会弃教的
我以为殉教将是我的救赎
I thought that martyrdom would be my salvation.
求你 上帝 别让它成为我的耻辱
Please, please, God, do not let it be my shame.
瞧 他个头真大
诗篇91:9 诗篇18:2
上帝是我的避难所 我的救主
The Lord is my refuge, and my deliverer.
诗篇54:4 希伯来书2:13
上帝是帮助我的 我要依赖他
My God is my helper, and in Him will I put my trust.
出自天主教神学家托马斯·阿奎纳所著赞美诗 《Pange Lingua Gloriosi Corporis Mysterium》
不朽的主 因救赎世人的使命 流尽鲜血
Of the Blood, all price exceeding, shed by our immortal King, destined for the world's redemption.
你跟着我做什么
Why are you following me?
别跟着我
Stop following me!
主啊 感谢您赐予我几日安宁
Thank you, Lord, for the gentle days here.
耶稣告诫我要爱所有人
Jesus taught me to love everyone.
可那些将我朋友折磨至死的人 我没办法去爱他们
But I cannot feel love to those who torture our friends to death.
我愤怒 我不能爱他们
I am angry. I cannot love them.
连守卫们都受到了您的感召 我的主
Even the guards have been touched by your hand, Lord.
我有罪恶感
I feel guilty.
我怀疑 这持续的平静
I wonder if this unbroken peace… From Him comes my salvation.
是否意味着 我死期将至
…is proof that my death is not far away.
…绝不动摇
I shall never be shaken.
绝不动摇
我清楚地看见您儿子的一生 几乎如同我自己的一般
I see the life of your son so clearly, almost like my own.
他的面庞 消弭了我所有的恐惧
And his face, it takes all fear from me.
那是我从儿时起 便铭记至今的面庞
It is the face I remember from childhood.
他向我诉说着
Speaking to me.
我能感觉到
I'm sure of it.
他承诺道 "我不会抛弃你"
Promising "I will not abandon you."
"我不会抛弃你"
"I will not abandon you."
把它穿上
Put them on.
我们的僧人就穿这个
You should be honored. It's what our priests wear.
罗德里格兹神父 来自葡萄牙 是吗
Father Rodrigues from Portugal, yes?
对不起 神父 我有些词不达意
I am sorry, Padre, for my speaking.
我的外语不是很好
My language is not so good.
筑后守:筑后国长官 后演变为衔位 筑后国为日本古代令制国之一
筑后守大人
But his Lordship, the Governor of Chikugo,
非常关心 你是否舒…舒服?
is anxious about your comfort.
舒服?
Comfort?
应该是 "不适"
Perhaps discomfort.
不适 是的
Discomfort. Yes.
至于你为何会在这里
About why you are here, and if you are not at ease,
对了 如果你感到不适 请告诉我们
please say so.
你远道而来 一路历经艰难险阻
Your trip was long. There were many dangers.
你的坚强意志 令我们深受触动
The power of your determination touches us greatly.
我们知道 你也饱受过煎熬
We know you have also suffered greatly.
我们不想再加重你的苦痛
We do not wish to add to your suffering.
一想到这次审问可能会令你不适 我们也很痛苦
And the thought that we might do so is painful for us, too.
谢谢
Thank you.
神父
Padre.
你带来的教义 在西班牙和葡萄牙也许是真理
The doctrine you bring with you may be true in Spain and Portugal,
但我们仔细研究
but we have studied it carefully.
久经思考以后
Thought about it over much time.
认为它在日本没有用处 没有价值
And find it is of no use and of no value in Japan.
我们的结论是 它是一种威胁
We have concluded that it is a danger.
但我们相信 我们为你们带来了真理
But we believe we have brought you the truth.
真理是普世的
The truth is universal.
真理是各国共有的 贯通古今的 因此才叫真理
It's common to all countries at all times. That's why we call it the truth.
如果教义在葡萄牙是真理 却在日本不是
If a doctrine weren't as true here in Japan as it is in Portugal,
那它就根本不是真理
then we couldn't call it the truth.
我们注意到 你没有干过农活 神父
I see you do not work with your hands, Father.
可是众所周知 在一方水土生长茂盛的树
But everyone knows a tree which flourishes in one kind of earth
在另一方水土 可能会腐烂死亡
may decay and die in another.
基督教的树同样如此 它的叶子在此腐烂
It is the same with the tree of Christianity. The leaves decay here.
它的枝芽无法生存
The buds die.
杀死枝芽的不是这片土壤
It is not the soil that has killed the buds.
这里本来有三十万基督徒 就在日本 直到这片土壤被…
There were 300,000 Christians here in Japan before the soil was…
被?
Yes?
被毒害
Was poisoned.
你不作任何回应吗
You have no reply?
你何必回应呢
And why should you? You're…
你们永远改变不了我的心
You're never going to change my heart.
而且似乎我也改变不了你们的
And it seems like I'm not going to change yours.
你们想要考验我的信念? 那就给我真正的挑战
You want to test my faith? Give me a real challenge.
带我去见长崎奉行
Bring me to the Inquisitor.
带我去见井上大人
Bring me to Inoue-sama.
他们在笑什么
Why are they laughing?
我说的一点都不好笑 他们在笑什么
I didn't say anything funny. Why are they laughing?
因为 神父
Because, Padre…
因为
Because…
我就是筑后守
I am the Governor of Chikugo.
我就是长崎奉行
I am the Inquisitor.
我就是井上
I am Inoue.
他们要这样在雨中工作多久?
How long… How long will they have to work like this in the rain?
直到做完
Until finished.
神父 神父 神父
Padre. Padre! Padre!
请听我说
Please listen to me.
他们威胁我
Please listen to me!
我从没有收过他们的钱
I never took their money!
我没有为了钱出卖您
I did not betray you for money!
请救救我们的主
要提防他 神父
Be careful of him, Padre.
也许井上大人给了他钱 利用他来欺骗我们
Maybe Inoue-sama pays him to make us trample.
不 他没有
No, he did not!
求求您 神父 让我忏悔吧
Please, Padre. Let me confess.
神父
Padre…
我知道 我臭不可闻
I know I smell.
我浑身是罪孽的臭气
I smell of sin.
但我想再忏悔一次 让主洗去我的罪孽
I want to confess again so the Lord can wash me clean.
你为什么来这里?
Why did you come here?
是为了得到主的赦免吗
Is it for absolution?
你到底懂不懂什么叫赦免?
Do you have any understanding what absolution is?
那您明白我所说的吗
Do you understand what I've been saying?
要是早生十年
Years ago,
我就可以像一个优秀的基督徒那样死去
I could have died a good Christian.
那时还没有迫害
There was no persecution!
为什么我那么晚才出生?
Why was I born now?
这不公平
This is so unfair!
我很抱歉
I am sorry.
那你到底还信不信?
But do you still believe?
以圣父 圣子 圣灵之名
In nomine Patris, et Filii, et Spiritus Sancti.
保佑我吧 神父 我犯下了罪
Bless me, Padre, for I have sinned.
我很抱歉 我如此懦弱
I am sorry for being so weak.
我很抱歉 发生了这种事情
I am sorry this has happened.
我很抱歉 我对你做的事
I am sorry for what I did to you.
帮帮我 神父 带走我的罪孽
Help me, Padre. Take away the sin.
我会再次努力变强大的
I will try again to be strong!
主啊 耶稣为何会怜爱这样的肮脏之人?
Father, how could Jesus love a wretch like this?
这里弥漫着邪恶的气息 可是恶人也有恶人的坚强和美
There is evil all around in this place. I sense its strength, even its beauty.
但这个人身上什么也没有
But there is none of that in this man.
他甚至不值得被称作 "恶人"
He is not worthy to be called evil.
（葡萄牙语）
愿你平安
Go in peace.
我觉得…
I feel…
我害怕…
I… I fear. Jesus, forgive me.
耶稣啊 原谅我 我也许不配称你的名
I may not be worthy of you.
这只是走个形式罢了
踩一下就行 不是真心的也可以
只是把脚放在上面 并不会使你们背离信仰
我真的不在乎
你们越快做完
就越早不用被太阳晒
就用脚碰一下 轻轻踩也可以
随便怎么做都行
我将立刻给予你们自由
Ikitsuki-jima, Kuboura, Chokichi.
只是一幅画像而已
把脚放上去
快点
下一个
Onajiku, Haru.
你呢
你这样是没有意义的
快点
下一个
Onajiku, Tobe.
你可以轻轻地踩
然后就自由了
快点
就踩一下
踩吧
下一个
Onajiku, Wataichi.
就踩一下
快点
你一定很想要自由
自由
把脚放上去
把他们都带回去
那一个留下
主啊 感谢您聆听我的祈祷
Thank you, Lord, for hearing my prayer.
这就是基督徒的下场
但是
我会告诉你们 怎样可以避免那种下场
带他过来
来吧
把脚放上去
非常简单的
我承认他不是第一次做了
但是看啊 这个动作多简单
比鞠躬还简单
不是吗
走吧
滚蛋
滚出去
看到了吗
他做到了他要做的
仅仅如此
抱歉这几天忽视了您 神父
Ah. I'm sorry I've neglected you for some days now, Padre.
我在平户有事情要忙
But I had business in Hirado.
我希望您哪天也能去那里看看
I hope you get to go there yourself sometime.
那里一定很美
I'm sure it's very beautiful.
大名:日本古代封建制度对领主的称呼
关于统治那里的大名 有一个有趣的故事
There is an interesting story about the daimyo who ruled there.
他有四个妾室 四个 都很漂亮 但是….
He had four concubines. Four! They were all beautiful, but they…
抱歉 这可能不是个好故事 对一个禁欲的神父来说
I'm sorry. Maybe this is not a story for a celibate priest.
没关系 请继续
It's all right. Please go on.
总之 大名的妾室们妒忌心都很强
In that case, the daimyo's concubines were all jealous
她们明争暗斗 没完没了
and they fought and fought without end.
所以这位平户大名 把她们赶出了府邸
So the daimyo of Hirado drove them away from his castle,
于是他的生活重归平静
and peace came into his life again.
你觉得这个故事有什么意义吗
Do you think this story has a lesson?
有
Yes.
这是一个很明智的人
That this was a very wise man.
我很高兴 你和我的看法相同 这位大名就像日本
I'm glad. That means you understand the daimyo is like Japan,
而这些妾室就是西班牙 葡萄牙 荷兰 英国
and these concubines are Spain, Portugal, Holland, England.
每个人都想赢过对方 这座府邸渐渐地就被毁掉了
Each trying to gain the advantage against the other and destroy the house in the process!
既然你认为这个人很明智
Since you say this man is wise,
那你肯定能理解 为何我们一定要禁止基督徒
you will understand why we must outlaw the Christian.
其实 我们基督教主张一夫一妻制
Well, our church teaches monogamy.
一位妻子
-One wife. -Uh-huh.
如果日本需要从四位之中 选择一位合法妻子呢
What if Japan were to choose one lawful wife from the four?
你是说葡萄牙吗
You mean Portugal.
我是指基督教
No. I mean, the Holy Church.
难道你不觉得 一个男人更应当
Don't you think it would be better for the man
忘掉那些外国女人 而选择本国的女人吗
to forget about foreign women and choose one of his own?
在婚姻里 国籍并不重要
Nationality is not so important when it comes to a marriage.
重要的是爱 爱与忠诚
What matters is love. Love and fidelity.
爱? 神父 有太多太多男人 因为丑女人固执的爱 而深受困扰了
Ah, love. Padre, there are men who are plagued by the persistent love of an ugly woman.
传教士对您来说
Is that what missionary work is to you?
就是丑女人吗
An ugly woman?
是的
Yes.
不能生小孩的女人 怎么说
不育者
Barren.
不育的女人 当不了真正的妻子
A barren woman cannot be a true wife.
如果上帝的福音在此迷失了方向 这并不是教会的错
If the gospel has lost its way here, it's not the fault of the church.
错的是有人夺去了教徒的信仰 就像夺走丈夫之妻一般
It is the fault of those who tear away the faithful from their faith like a husband from a wife.
你是说 我吗
You mean me?
神父 你的传教士似乎不了解日本
Padre, you missionaries do not seem to know Japan.
而您 尊敬的奉行 似乎也不了解基督教
And you, Honorable Inquisitor, do not seem to know Christianity.
有些人把你们的宗教视为诅咒
There are those who think of your religion as a curse.
我不这样认为 我的看法不同
I do not. I see it in another way.
但它依旧很危险
But still dangerous.
我希望你想想 丑女人固执的爱
I'd like you to think about the persistent love of an ugly woman
想想不育的女人永远当不了妻子
and how a barren woman should never be a wife.
神父 救我
Padre! Padre! Help me, Padre! Help me, please!
神父 请救救我
Padre! Padre!
神父
Padre!
你们要带她们去哪里
Where are you taking them?
神父
Padre! Padre! Padre!
您今天要出远门了
You are traveling today.
请坐 坐着对您更好 请坐
Sit down. It's better for you, I think. Please.
神父 今天感觉怎么样
Padre. How are you feeling today, eh?
我敢说空气绝对新鲜 即使您正处于我们最新的牢房中
I'm sure the air must feel good even though you were in our newest prison.
旧牢房太为难神父们了
The old prison was very tough on the padres.
风吹雨淋的 很糟糕 抱歉 请问
-Rain, wind… -Sorry. Excuse me.
井上大人什么时候到
When will Inoue-sama be here?
他今天不过来
Oh. He's not coming today.
你想他了吗
Do you miss him?
他对待我很好 为我提供一日三餐 想让我的身体背叛我的心
He treats me kindly. Three meals a day so that my body will betray my heart.
这就是你们的计划 不是吗
That's your plan, isn't it?
你们就在等这一天吧
That's what you're waiting for.
完全不是 不过我们今天确实在等一个人
-Not at all. -No? But we are waiting for someone today.
井上大人想让你见见他
Inoue-sama wants you to meet him.
他随时可能到 他也是葡萄牙人 和你一样
He will be here any moment. He's Portuguese like yourself.
你们应该有很多话要聊
You should have a lot to talk about, huh?
费雷拉
Ferreira.
是你猜的那个人吗
Is it who you expected?
-我想和他谈谈 -别急
-I want to talk to him. -There's no hurry.
还很早 时间多得是
It is early. Plenty of time.
告诉我 他知道我在这里吗
Tell me. Does he know I'm here?
奉行所:奉行的办公场所 相当于中国的"衙门"
不行 我不能告诉你奉行所的事务
I cannot tell you. I must not speak about the business of the Inquisitor's office.
但我可以告诉你
But I can tell you
他知道你还活着 因为我们告诉他 你弃教了
he knows you are alive because we told him you apostatized.
现在 你知道那些草垫的用处了吗
Now, do you know what they use those mats for?
不
No.
看 上帝会怎么说? 可能会说…
Look. The guard. What could he be saying to Father Garupe? Maybe this.
"如果你是一个真正的基督徒 你会弃教
If you are truly a Christian, you will apostatize
你不会让他们丧命"
and not let them die.
奉行大人承诺 只要葛尔贝神父弃教 就放了那四个人
You know, the Inquisitor promises that if Father Garupe apostatizes, the four will be free.
我希望葛尔贝神父能同意
I hope Father Garupe agrees.
我应该告诉你 这些基督徒已经在奉行所践踏过圣像了
I should tell you, these Christians already trampled and denied their faith at the Inquisitor's office.
他们照你们说的做了 就放了他们吧
If they did what you wanted, then let them go.
他们照你们说的做了
Let them go. They did what you wanted.
放过他们 求求你们 放了他们
So let them go. Please. Please! Please! Please! Let them go!
我们不在乎他们 四个农民?
We don't want them. Four farmers?
在沿海诸岛 还有数百个基督徒农民
There are still hundreds of Christian peasants on the islands off the coast. -No! -We want the Padre to deny,
我们希望神父能弃教 给他们做个榜样
We want the Padre to deny, and be an example to them.
停下
No, please!
弃教吧 弃教吧
Oh, apostatize! Apostatize!
主啊 救救他们吧 不要把这些留给我们面对
For their sake, Lord, do not leave this to us! Take me instead!
不
No!
不要 葛尔贝 不要
No, no, no! Garupe, no!
不 不 不 不
No, no, no! No!
不
No!
不 请停下
Oh, please! Please, please!
惨不忍睹啊 惨不忍睹
Terrible business! Terrible!
无论看多少次 都觉得可怕
No matter how many times you see it.
想想你让这些人所受的罪吧
Think about the suffering you have inflicted on these people
就因为你那传教到日本的自私美梦
just because of your selfish dream of a Christian Japan.
你的上帝给日本带来了惩罚 通过你
Your Deus punishes Japan through you!
至少葛尔贝神父是清白的
At least Garupe was clean.
而你呢
But you, you have no will!
你毫无意志 你不配被称作神父
You do not deserve to be called a priest.
主啊 主啊 为何你要抛弃我们
My God. My God. Why have you forsaken me? Why have you forsaken me?
你的儿子在哪里
I was your son.
你的儿子在十字架上
Your son was going to the cross.
你沉默着 即使对着他
You were silent, even to him.
沉默 冰冷的沉默
Your silent, cold son.
不 不
Oh, no, no.
荒唐 荒唐
Ludicrous. Ludicrous.
愚蠢
Stupid. Stupid.
他不会回应的
He's not going to answer.
您要进去看看吗
再等等吧
神父
Padre.
出来吧 神父
Come along, Padre.
我们的僧人不太喜欢你们神父 但你还是能在此发现许多价值
Our priests do not like your priests, but you will still find much of value here.
怎么了 神父 不习惯这个气味吗
What is it, Padre? The incense?
肉的气味?
The smell of meat?
你吃过肉吗 来到日本以后
Have you had any meat since you came to Japan?
我就不太喜欢这气味
I don't much like the smell, myself.
你有没有猜过
Have you guessed yet?
有没有猜过谁会来
Have you guessed who's coming?
这是井上大人的命令
This is Inoue-sama's command
也是这个人的愿望
and the other's wish.
这个人?
The other?
我们的天父啊…
Our Father, who art in heaven, hallowed be thy name, thy kingdom come, thy will be done…
神父 想想那些你能拯救的灵魂
Padre, think of the souls you can save,
费雷拉神父
Padre Ferreira.
Fa…
神父
Father…
费雷拉神父
Father Ferreira.
我放弃了
I'd given up.
神父 我们这么久没见了
So long since we have met.
求求您 说点什么吧
Please say something.
我又能对你说什么呢 在这样的场合
What can I say to you on such an occasion?
您要是对我还有一丝怜悯 说点什么吧
If you have any pity for me, say something.
您在这里住了很久吗
Have you… Have you… Have you been living here for long?
差不多一年了 我估计
About a year, I suppose.
这是什么地方
Why? What is this place?
寺院 我学习的地方
A temple where I study.
我也在长崎的某个牢房里 我不知道具体位置
I'm in… I'm in a sort of prison somewhere in Nagasaki. I don't know precisely where.
我知道
I know it.
您曾是我的导师
You were my teacher.
是我的告解神父 我的导师 我依然是
You were my confessor. -My teacher. -I'm much the same.
帮我一个举手之劳
Do a single simple thing.
告诉我 神父 告诉我你同意
Tell me then, Padre. Tell me you agree.
我看上去真的不一样了吗
Do I… Do I really seem so different?
泽野阁下每天都在写书
The Honorable Sawano spends his day writing
关于天文学的
about astronomy.
这是井上大人的命令
At Inoue-sama's order.
日本人有着非常丰富的知识
There is great knowledge here.
但医学和天文学方面 仍有待学习
But in, uh, medicine and astronomy, much remains to be taught.
我很高兴能帮上忙
I'm happy to help.
我也感到满足 自己终于能对这个国家有所贡献
It is fulfilling to finally be of use in this country.
所以你感到幸福吗 神父
Then you're happy, Father?
我说过了
I said so.
说说你正在写的另一本书
Mention the other book you are writing.
这本书叫《显伪录》
It is called Kengiroku.
它指出了基督教的错误
It shows the errors of Christianity
反驳了上帝的教义
and refutes the teachings of Deus.
你知道书名的含义吗
Do you understand the title?
告诉他
Tell him.
意思是 揭露谎言 或者说 撕开虚伪的面具 要是你喜欢更华丽的辞藻
It means deceit disclosed, or unmasked, if you prefer a more florid reading.
奉行阁下已经看过手稿了
His Lordship, the Inquisitor, he praises it.
他赞不绝口 说我完成得很好
He says it is well done.
你把真理当作毒药使用
You use the truth like poison!
一位神父口出此言 真是有趣
What a funny thing for a priest to say.
太残忍了 这比任何酷刑都残忍
This is cruel. Cruel. Worse than any torture
用这种方式扭曲一个人的灵魂
to twist a man's soul in this way.
我觉得 你是在说你自己吧 神父
I think you must be speaking of yourself.
而不是说泽野忠庵
Not of Sawano Chūan.
他 谁
-Who? -Him!
费雷拉这个名字 只是对你而言
He is Ferreira only to you.
他现在是泽野忠庵了
He is Sawano Chūan now.
一个已经寻找到平静的人
A man who has found peace.
让他引领你的道路吧
Let him guide you along his path.
恩慈之路
The path of mercy.
这意味着 你必须抛弃自我
That means only that you abandon self.
没人有资格干预他人的内心
No one should interfere with another man's spirit.
帮助他人 是佛的道路 也是你的道路
To help others is the way of the Buddha and your way, too.
两个宗教 在这一点上是相同的
The two religions are the same in this.
根本没有必要争个你高我低 它们有着如此多的共同点
It is not necessary to win anyone over to one side or another when there is so much to share.
接着说
Go on.
他们让我说服你抛弃你的信仰
I've been told to get you to abandon the faith.
这个
This…
这是在穴吊时留下的
This is from the pit.
你被绑住 无法动弹 然后倒吊起来
You're tied so you can't move and hung upside down.
划一道切口
An incision is made.
你能感觉到鲜血一滴一滴流下来
You feel the blood dripping down, drop by drop,
这样你就不会头部充血 也就不会死得太快
so it doesn't run to your head and you won't die too soon.
践踏你的耶稣
Step on your Jesus.
你是这里唯一剩下的神父了
You are the last priest left here now, Padre.
我相信井上大人也不想再动用穴吊了
I'm sure Inoue-sama will be pleased to put an end to the pain.
他是个务实的人 神父
He's a practical man, Padre.
不是暴君
Not a cruel one.
我在这个国家传教了十五年
I have labored in this country for 15 years.
我比你更了解它
I know it better than you.
我们的信仰无法在这个国家扎根
Our religion does not take root in this country.
因为根已经被切断了
Because the roots have been torn up.
不 因为这个国家就是一片沼泽
No! Because this country is a swamp.
什么都生长不了
Nothing grows here.
任何一根苗种在这里 它的根都会腐烂
Plant a sapling here and the roots rot.
基督教就曾经在这里生长 长得枝繁叶茂
There was a time when Christianity grew and flourished here.
什么时候
-When? -When?
在您的时代 神父
In your time, Father.
就在您的时代 在您变成…
In your time, before you became like…
变成什么 变成他们吗
Like who? Like them?
罗德里格斯 请听我说
Rodrigues, please listen.
日本人只相信经过他们歪曲以后的上帝福音
The Japanese only believe in their distortion of our gospel.
所以他们其实根本不相信
So they did not believe at all.
他们从来没相信过
They never believed.
您怎么能这么说
How can you say that?
从圣方济各的时代 直到您的时代
From the time of St. Francis Xavier through your own time.
这里涌现了成千上万的皈依者
There were hundreds of thousands of converts here.
皈依者 皈依者 没错
-Converts? -Converts, yes!
圣方济各来到这里
Francis Xavier came here
向日本人介绍上帝之子
to teach the Japanese about the Son of God.
但他首先要问问 日本人如何称呼上帝
But first he had to ask how to refer to God.
大日:即大日如来佛 日本真言宗最崇高的神
大日 人们这么告诉他
"Dainichi," he was told.
要不要见识下 他们的大日是什么
And shall I show you their Dainichi?
看啊 那就是太阳之神
Behold. There is the Son of God.
上帝唯一的子嗣
God's only begotten Son.
在圣经中 耶稣在死后第三天重生
In the scriptures, Jesus rose on the third day.
而在日本 太阳之神每天都会重新升起
In Japan, …the Son of God rises daily.
日本人无法想象 那些超越自然的存在
The Japanese cannot think of an existence beyond the realm of nature.
对他们来说 没有事物能超越人类存在
For them, nothing transcends a human.
不
-No. -They can't conceive
他们想象不出我们上帝的概念
of our idea of the Christian God.
你错了 你错了 他们崇拜上帝
No, you're wrong. You're wrong. They worship God. God! Our Lord.
上帝 我们的主 他们赞颂上帝的名
They praise the name of Deus.
那只不过是又一个名词 来指代他们闻所未闻的神
That's just another word for a god they never knew.
我看着人们死去
I saw men die!
我也是
I did, too.
为上帝而死 心怀着信仰被烧死
For Deus! On fire with their faith!
那些殉道者的确被烧死了 神父
Your martyrs may have been on fire, Father,
可他们并没有心怀基督教的信仰
but it was not for the Christian faith.
我看着他们牺牲 我看着他们牺牲
I saw them die. I saw them die.
他们不是白白牺牲的
They did not die for nothing.
的确不是
They did not.
他们牺牲是因为你 罗德里格斯
They're dying for you, Rodrigues.
你救过几个人?
How many did you save
当你践踏在我们上帝脸上的时候?
when you trampled on the face of our Lord?
几个人? 除了你自己
How many beside yourself?
我不知道
I don't know.
肯定没有你能够拯救的多
Certainly not as many as you may help.
你只是在为自己的软弱寻找借口
You're trying to justify your own weakness.
愿上帝怜悯你
God have mercy on you.
哪个上帝 哪一个
Which god? Which one?
我们常说 "江山…"
We say…
抱歉 你还未完全掌握这门语言 对吧
I'm sorry. You haven't learned the language thoroughly, have you?
这里有句谚语
There's a saying here.
"江山易改 本性难移"
Mountains and rivers can be moved, but man's nature cannot be moved.
这句谚语充满了智慧 如同这里的许多事物
It's very wise, like so much here.
我们在日本找到了自己的本性 罗德里格斯
We find our original nature in Japan, Rodrigues.
也许 这就是追寻上帝的真正意义
Perhaps it's what's meant by finding God.
你是个耻辱
You're a disgrace.
你是个耻辱 神父
You're a disgrace, Father.
我都无法再称呼你神父了
I can't… I can't even call you that anymore.
很好 我现在有个日本名字
Good. I have a Japanese name now,
还有了妻子 孩子
and a wife, and children.
他们是一个死刑犯的遗孀和遗孤
I inherited them all from an executed man.
你有什么感想
How do you feel?
他向你展示了恩慈之路
He has shown you the path of mercy.
我希望你能跟随他
I hope you take it.
你为什么不把我吊在洞里
Why don't you just hang me in the pit?
奉行所传唤你
神父 你为他们而来 他们却恨你入骨
Padre, you came here for them and they all hate you.
随你怎么羞辱我 这样只会给我更多勇气
Insult me all you like. You just give me more courage.
你今晚就会弃教的
You will need it tonight.
你是一个好人 神父
You are a good man, Padre.
你忍受不了苦难
You cannot stand suffering.
无论是你自己 还是别人的
Your own or others'.
井上大人说你今晚就会弃教
Inoue-sama says you will apostatize tonight.
他预料到了费雷拉的弃教
He was right about Ferreira.
你也不会例外
And he's right about you.
上帝救救我 耶稣救救我
God help me. Jesus help me.
马可福音14:34 花园即耶稣因犹大出卖而被捕的客西马尼花园
在花园里 您说
In the garden, You said,
我心里甚是忧伤 几乎要死去
"Thy soul is sorrowful even unto death."
我愿为您流血
I would bleed for you.
我愿 我愿为您而死 只要我知道您在
I would. I would die for you if I knew you…
您是否与我同在
Are you here with me?
神父 原谅我 神父
Padre. Forgive me.
神父 我是来忏悔的
Padre! I came here to make confession.
神父
Padre!
原谅我 原谅我吧 神父
Forgive me, Padre!
原谅我
Forgive me!
停下 停下这声音 快救救他
Stop it! Stop it! Stop it! Stop the noise! Stop it! Someone help him!
你要干什么 不是我 是下面
-What do you need? -Not me. Down there.
有个人很痛苦
There is a man in agony
可是守卫却酣睡着 鼾声震天 像条野狗一样
and the guard is sound asleep and snoring like a wild dog!
你以为那声音是守卫的?
You think that noise is the guard?
难以置信
Incredible.
泽野 告诉他 那是什么
Sawano, tell him. Say what it is.
那不是守卫 也不是鼾声
It is not the guard and it's not snoring.
是基督徒的声音 一共有五个人 事实上
It's Christians. Five of them, in fact.
都吊在洞里
All hanging in the pit.
你发现墙上的字了吗
Have you found the words on the wall?
"赞美他吧"
"Laudate eum." "Praise Him."
当时我在这牢房里用石头刻的
I cut them there with a stone when I was in this cell.
和你一样
Like you.
你没有资格和我说话
You have no right to speak to me.
我有资格 因为你和我一样
Oh, I do. Because you are just like me.
你知道耶稣在客西马尼花园的经历
You see Jesus in Gethsemane
你以为你所受的考验和他一样
and believe your trial is the same as His.
洞里的那五个人也正在受苦 就像耶稣一样
Those five in the pit are suffering, too, just like Jesus,
但他们没有你这么自负
but they don't have your pride.
他们不会将自己比作耶稣
They would never compare themselves to Jesus.
你有资格让他们受苦吗
Do you have the right to make them suffer?
我曾经也在这间牢房里 听过外面痛苦的呻吟
I heard the cries of suffering in this same cell.
而我采取了行动
And I acted.
你在为自己找借口 你在为自己找借口
You excuse yourself! You excuse yourself!
这是黑暗的邪灵
That is the spirit of darkness.
你能为他们做什么 祈祷吗
And what would you do for them? Pray?
你得到回应了吗 只有更多的苦难
And get what in return? Only more suffering.
能终止这苦难的 只有你 而不是上帝
A suffering only you can end. Not God!
离我远点
Go away from me.
我也祈祷过 罗德里格斯
I prayed, too, Rodrigues.
没有用的
It doesn't help.
继续 祈祷吧
Go on. Pray.
但是要睁着双眼祈祷
But pray with your eyes open.
你可以解救他们
You can spare them.
他们呼喊着求助 如同你向上帝求助
They call out for help just as you call to God.
他沉默着 而你可以不沉默
He is silent, but you do not have to be.
他们应该弃教 弃教吧
They should apostatize. Apostatize!
上帝帮帮我 弃教啊 "Korobu" "Korobu"
God help me. Apostatize! Korobu! Korobu!
他们早已经弃教了
But they have apostatized.
弃了无数次了
Many times over.
他们是因为你才来到这里 罗德里格斯
They're here for you, Rodrigues.
只要你不弃教 他们就无法得救
As long as you don't apostatize, they cannot be saved.
一位神父应当像主一样行事
A priest should act in imitation of Christ.
要是主在这里
If Christ were here…
要是主在这里 他一定会有所行动的
If Christ were here, He would've acted.
弃教吧 为了他们
Apostatized for their sake.
不 不 主就在这里
No. No, He's here.
我只是听不见他
Christ is here. I just can't hear Him.
让上帝知道你爱他
Show God you love Him!
救下他所爱的子民吧
Save the lives of the people He loves.
有些事情要远远重于
There is something more important
教会的评判
than the judgment of the Church.
你现在将要做的是
You are now going to fulfill the most painful act of love
有史以来 最痛苦的爱的行为
that has ever been performed.
这只是形式而已
It's only a formality.
只是形式而已
Just a formality.
上前来 没关系的
Come ahead, now. It's all right.
踩踏我吧
Step on Me.
我理解你的痛苦
I understand your pain.
我来到这个世界 就是为了分担人们的痛苦
I was born into this world to share men's pain.
我背负十字架 是为了分担你们的痛苦
I carried this cross for your pain.
你的生命现已与我同在
Your life is with Me now.
踩吧
Step.
保罗:圣经人物 曾弃教并参与迫害基督徒
弃教的保罗
1641年
It was in the year 1641,
在我的首次日本之行中
during the first of my voyages to Japan,
我 迪耶特·亚伯希特
that I, Dieter Albrecht,
偶然成为了这段不可思议的故事中的一员
came upon the most extraordinary story in these pages.
基督
Christian.
非基督
Non-Christian.
作为一家荷兰贸易公司的医师 我周游四方
As a physician in a great Dutch trading company, I traveled widely.
基督
Christian.
但旅途中我所记叙的任何一个故事
But none of the wonders I have recounted in this journal
都比不上这个故事极富争议
has been so commented on
一段奇闻异事
as the curious matter…
非基督
Non-Christian.
一位弃教神父
…of the apostate priests.
基督
Christian.
我比任何一位欧洲编年史家 都更加接近
I came closer than any European chronicler
这个国家的不解之谜
to the enigma of this country.
非基督
Non-Christian.
以及这些迷失掉的神父的生活
And to learning of the lives of the lost priests.
井上奉行会突击搜查民宅
Inoue, the Inquisitor, would raid homes
搜寻一切有基督教图案的物件
and search for any objects with hidden Christian images.
基督
Christian.
两位神父受命检查这些物件 鉴别它们的用途
The two priests were required to examine these things and verify their use.
我甚至亲自观察过
I even, on occasion, observed them myself.
当时的荷兰人 是唯一获准进入日本经商的欧洲人
The Dutch were the only Europeans allowed to trade in Japan.
所有的船都要接受检查 确保没有走私宗教物品
All ships were searched to warrant they were not smuggling religious objects.
任何带有十字架 圣像或念珠的物品 都无法通过
Nothing bearing the images of the cross, a saint, or rosary could pass.
尽管监管严格 有些东西不可避免地走私了进来
Despite every attempt, a few things inevitably were smuggled in.
基督
Christian.
于是 日本人丢弃这个信仰的速度 如同鲜血溢出一样迅疾
And then it was as distressing to the Japanese as if blood had been spilled.
（荷兰语）
我们被教导 应当爱那些蔑视我们的人
We were taught to love those who scorned us.
我对他们毫无感情
I feel nothing for them.
只有我们的主 才可以评判你的内心
Only our Lord can judge your heart.
你刚刚说了 "我们的主"
You said, "Our Lord."
你听错了
I doubt it.
泽野忠庵死后
When Sawano Chūan died,
另一位神父以优异的表现接替了他的工作
the other priest assumed his duties and performed them with distinction.
到这时 他已能说出流利日语
By this time, I observed he had acquired considerable skill with the language.
并且似乎安于现状
And seemed to be at peace with his situation.
我有个好消息
I have good news.
有个男人在江户去世了 冈田三右卫门
A man has died in Edo. Okada San'emon.
他的名字可以给你
You will take his name just as it is.
他有家室 一妻一子
He had a household, and a wife and son.
她可以做你的妻子
You can take her as your wife.
有伴侣的男人工作效率最高
A man works best when he's not alone.
你要知道生月岛和五岛…
You should know that on the islands of Ikitsuki and Gotō… Uh… No.
那里还有很多农民 认为自己是基督徒
There are still many farmers who think themselves Christian.
你喜欢那样吗? 他们可以继续当基督徒
Do you like that? They can continue to be Christian.
你也许能从中得到些许满足
You may take some satisfaction in that,
毕竟根已经被切断了
because the roots are cut.
沼泽里什么都生长不了
Nothing grows in a swamp.
没错 日本就是这样的国家
Yes, Japan is that kind of country.
你们带给我们的基督教
The religion of the Christian you brought us
已经变成了一种陌生的东西
has become a strange thing.
它变了
It's changed.
你不是输给了我
You were not defeated by me.
你输给了日本这片沼泽
You were defeated by this swamp of Japan.
欢迎你
Welcome.
冈田三右卫门在江户度过了他的余生
Okada San'emon lived in Edo for the remaining years of his life.
十几年后 我获准进入江户
Some 10 years later, I was allowed to visit Edo.
日本人时常谈起冈田三右卫门
The Japanese gossiped freely about Okada San'emon.
井上奉行
The Inquisitor Inoue,
反复让他书写弃教保证书
demanded repeated vows of apostasy from him.
据他们所说
And they say,
这位堕落神父的回应 总是那么迅速而踊跃
"The fallen priest supplied them all quickly "and vigorously."
我听说奉行派人来找您了
I heard the Inquisitor sent his men for you.
有什么麻烦吗 没有
-Was there trouble? -No.
没有 只是
No, no. Just…
他们只是想确认我写完了
He only wanted to make sure I wrote the "korobi-shoumon."
最新的弃教保证书
My latest oath of renunciation.
谢谢你
Thank you.
万分感谢
ありがとうございました
您没什么要感谢我的
感谢你一直陪着我
For being here with me.
一緒にいってくれてありがとう
神父
Padre…
不 不 我不是 我不再是神父了
No. No. I'm not… I'm not anymore.
我是个堕落的神父
I'm a fallen priest.
但您是剩下的最后一位神父了
But you are the last priest left.
您依然可以听我忏悔
You could still hear my confession.
不 我不能
No, I can't.
No! I can't!
我还是为我的所作所为而痛苦 神父
I still suffer for what I did, Padre.
我背叛了您 背叛了我的家人 背叛了我们的主
I betrayed you. I betrayed my family. I betrayed our Lord.
求求您 听我忏悔吧
Please… Hear my confession.
神父
Padre.
主啊 我与你的沉默做斗争
Lord, I fought against your silence.
我在你身旁一同受苦 我从未沉默
I suffered beside you. I was never silent.
我知道
I know.
但即使上帝沉默了 我的一生
But even if God had been silent my whole life,
截至今日 我在做的每件事 我做过的每件事
to this very day, everything I do, everything I've done…
都默念着他的名
Speaks of Him.
在这沉默之中 我听见了您的声音
It was in the silence that I heard Your voice.
奉行继续坚持 定期排查疑似的基督徒
The Inquisitor continued to insist on periodic examinations of all suspected Christians.
冈田三右卫门也不例外
Okada San'emon was not exempt from this.
井上决定让他的例子永远不被遗忘
Inoue was determined to never let his example be forgotten.
更确切地说 不要被神父本人所遗忘
Perhaps most particularly by the priest himself.
冈田三右卫门
Okada San'emon.
公元1667年 一个装有宗教图案的护身符
In the year 1667, a religious image was discovered inside an amulet
在一个叫吉次郎的仆人身上被搜出
belonging to a servant called Kichijiro.
这个仆人声称 这是从赌局上赢来的
The servant said he had won it gambling,
他从未打开看过
had never looked inside,
也绝不可能是冈田三右卫门给他的
and could never have gotten the amulet from Okada San'emon
因为他一直被守卫监视着
since he was always underguard.
仆人吉次郎被带走了
The servant Kichijiro was taken away.
此后 冈田三右卫门被严加看守
After that, Okada San'emon himself was carefully watched.
1682年 我最后一次远航日本 我问起他的消息
During my last voyage in 1682, I asked about him.
日本人迫不及待地告诉我
And the Japanese were eager to reply.
那最后一位神父 再也没有承认过上帝
The last priest never acknowledged the Christian God.
无论嘴上还是行动上
Not by word or symbol.
他再没有提过他的名 再没有祈祷过
He never spoke of Him and never prayed.
即使在死前也没有
Not even when he died.
他的信仰早已告终
The business of his faith was long ended.
三个守卫看管着他的棺木 直至它被抬走
Three guards stood watch over the coffin
只为以防万一
until it could be taken away, just to be certain.
只有她的妻子获准短暂瞻仰 她放入了一把小刀
Only his wife was briefly allowed to view the body, and place there, a humble mamorigatana
以驱散恶灵
to ward off evil spirits.
她没有任何流泪的迹象
There was no indication that she wept.
遗体以佛教仪式进行火化
The body was treated in the Buddhist manner.
他得到了一个圆寂后的法号
And he was given a posthumous Buddhist name.
这个曾经名叫罗德里格斯的男人 终于如他们所愿
The man who was once Rodrigues ended as they wanted.
亦如我初见他时那样 背弃着上帝
And as I first saw him, lost to God.
但对于这一点的真伪 只有上帝才能回答
But as to that, indeed, only God can answer.
导演:马丁·斯科塞斯
Martin Scorsese
Author:Shusaku Endo
原著:遠藤周作 えんどう しゅうさく [1923—1996] 出版于1966